<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" modified="2026-06-15T11:44:08.103Z" lasteditedby="tim" version="2" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title>Current Development Status</title>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>b dqa1</keyword>
    <keyword>boot milestone</keyword>
    <keyword>Cypress 82C693</keyword>
    <keyword>development status</keyword>
    <keyword>dka</keyword>
    <keyword>dva0</keyword>
    <keyword>LFU</keyword>
    <keyword>NVRAM</keyword>
    <keyword>OS boot</keyword>
    <keyword>PCI enumeration</keyword>
    <keyword>roadmap</keyword>
    <keyword>snapshot</keyword>
    <keyword>SRM prompt</keyword>
    <keyword>SROM</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1">Current Development Status</para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal">This page is a plain-language snapshot of where EmulatR stands as of June 2026 -- what works end to end, the milestone the project is working toward next, and the known rough edges. It is deliberately a moving target; the authoritative day-to-day record lives in the engineering journals and the dated CHECKPOINT notes. For a per-subsystem breakdown see the Feature Matrix.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">What works today</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">A clean cold boot runs the original, unmodified DEC SRM console firmware all the way to the interactive <text styleclass="Code Example">&gt;&gt;&gt;</text> prompt, fully usable over a serial terminal. The commands <text styleclass="Code Example">show config</text>, <text styleclass="Code Example">show memory</text>, <text styleclass="Code Example">show pal</text> and <text styleclass="Code Example">show version</text> all return correct output. Firmware is a real SRM 7.3-1 image carried in emulated flash; the LFU <text styleclass="Code Example">update srm</text> path works, and machine-state snapshots have been captured for both the firmware-update (<text styleclass="Code Example">UPD&gt;</text>) and console (<text styleclass="Code Example">&gt;&gt;&gt;</text>) states.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">The current frontier: getting to an OS boot</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The next major milestone is booting an operating system. Two concrete gaps stand between the prompt and that goal:</para>
    <para styleclass="NotesBox">No bootable disk is enumerated yet. At the prompt, show device lists only the floppy (dva0) -- there is no dka SCSI disk to boot from. Disk-image support and the storage backing exist (see Virtual Disk Images); the gap is the device model and enumeration that would make a disk appear to the firmware.</para>
    <para styleclass="NotesBox">On-board PCI devices are not walked. show config reports only the Cypress 82C693 bridge on PCI Hose 00 -- the on-board Ethernet and SCSI controllers are not yet modeled or enumerated, so the firmware cannot find them.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">A separate active investigation concerns the front-panel halt gate: <text styleclass="Code Example">b dqa1</text> currently reports &quot;BOOT NOT POSSIBLE&quot;. This is being diagnosed with an armed hardware trace to identify the exact source the firmware tests before any fix is written -- an evidence-first approach rather than guessing at a register.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">Known cosmetic issues</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">Two harmless display quirks are tracked: <text styleclass="Code Example">show device</text> prints each line twice (console line-doubling, also seen at <text styleclass="Code Example">UPD&gt;</text>), and the SROM revision shown by <text styleclass="Code Example">display</text> / <text styleclass="Code Example">show config</text> contains one garbled byte. Neither affects operation.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">What is planned next</para>
    <list id="0" type="ul" listtype="bullet" formatstring="&#183;" format-charset="SYMBOL_CHARSET" levelreset="true" legalstyle="false" startfrom="1" styleclass="NotesBox" style="font-family:Symbol; font-size:11pt; color:#000000;">
      <li styleclass="NotesBox"> SRM environment persistence -- make set at the prompt survive a reset and cold boot, like real NVRAM.</li>
      <li styleclass="NotesBox"> PCI bus enumeration with on-board device models (Ethernet, SCSI), so the firmware discovers real hardware instead of an all-ones placeholder.</li>
      <li styleclass="NotesBox"> A SCSI disk plus boot media so a dka device exists to boot, leading into an OS install from CD-ROM.</li>
    </list>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:10pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;">Snapshot date: June 2026. Because status changes frequently, treat this page as orientation and confirm specifics against the current build and the latest CHECKPOINT journal.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="SeeAlso">See Also.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Feature-Matrix">Feature Matrix</link></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Overview--------------------">Architecture Overview</link></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Halt-Button-is-IN_-BOOT-NOT-">Halt Button is IN, BOOT NOT POSSIBLE</link></para>
  </body>
</topic>
