<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" modified="2026-06-15T11:52:28.459Z" lasteditedby="tim" version="2" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title>Decompressor Internals</title>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>compressed firmware</keyword>
    <keyword>decom.c</keyword>
    <keyword>ev6_huf_decom.m64</keyword>
    <keyword>host_decompressor</keyword>
    <keyword>HW_RET</keyword>
    <keyword>inflate</keyword>
    <keyword>intercept-hybrid</keyword>
    <keyword>Mark Adler</keyword>
    <keyword>oracle</keyword>
    <keyword>SROM parameters</keyword>
    <keyword>WimC</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1">Decompressor Internals</para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal">This appendix is the source-level companion to the Firmware Decode &amp; Decompression page. It identifies the DEC sources behind the cold-boot self-decompression, the CPU/PAL side-effects the guest startup performs, and the native oracle EmulatR uses to prove its emulated CPU produces the correct image. Treat the DEC SRM sources as authoritative; AXPBox is not.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">What runs at cold boot</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The guest firmware ships compressed and decompresses itself on the emulated CPU every cold boot -- roughly 4 million cycles, visible as the spin at PC <text styleclass="Code Example">0x60111c</text>. The image carries a <text styleclass="Code Example">WimC</text> header (magic 0x436D6957) located by a linear scan; its longwords give the compressed size, the decompress target, and the start of the compressed data. For <text styleclass="Code Example">es45_v7_3.exe</text> the header sits at file offset 0x2400, the target is 0x8000, and the decompressed output is 0x30cc00 bytes (3,197,952).</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">The DEC sources</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The read-only originals live in <text styleclass="Code Example">Processor Support\Palcode\palcode\apisrm\apisrm\ref\</text>:</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <list id="0" type="ul" listtype="bullet" formatstring="&#183;" format-charset="SYMBOL_CHARSET" levelreset="true" legalstyle="false" startfrom="1" styleclass="NotesBox" style="font-family:Symbol; font-size:11pt; color:#000000;">
      <li styleclass="NotesBox">inflate.c -- the engine: Mark Adler inflate, version c10p1.</li>
      <li styleclass="NotesBox">decom.c -- the DEC wrapper providing main() and decompress().</li>
      <li styleclass="NotesBox">decomp.h -- types and the ROM / non-ROM switches.</li>
      <li styleclass="NotesBox">ev6_huf_decom.m64 -- the guest assembly startup that calls decompress().</li>
    </list>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">The startup is more than a memcpy</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The <text styleclass="Code Example">ev6_huf_decom.m64</text> startup is not a pure decompression: before and around the call it performs real CPU/PAL state setup -- it loads PAL_BASE, sets the I_CTL SDE bits, flushes the ITB / DTB and the I-cache, manages shadow registers, and saves and restores the SROM parameters in R16-R21. Any alternate &quot;host decompress&quot; path must preserve that end state, which is why a full bypass is risky and the recommended future design is an intercept-hybrid rather than a wholesale skip.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">The native oracle</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Code Example">tools/host_decompressor/</text> builds the SAME algorithm DEC used, from the SAME sources the firmware was compiled from, as a native host program with no emulation involved. Its harness <text styleclass="Code Example">oracle.c</text> replaces <text styleclass="Code Example">decom.c</text>&apos;s <text styleclass="Code Example">main()</text>: it finds the WimC header, sets the input/output pointers and compressed size, calls <text styleclass="Code Example">inflate()</text>, and dumps the image to <text styleclass="Code Example">ref_decompressed.bin</text>. The output matches EmulatR&apos;s emulated-CPU decompression byte for byte, which makes it a trusted regression guard. This is strictly stronger than AXPBox&apos;s <text styleclass="Code Example">decompressed.rom</text>, which is produced by running the guest decompressor on AXPBox&apos;s own emulated CPU (and so still depends on a correct CPU and a contrived entry sequence).</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The oracle settled the &quot;single-bit PAL corruption&quot; question: the instruction at PC <text styleclass="Code Example">0xd954</text> (encoding <text styleclass="Code Example">0x7be2a000 = hw_ret R2</text>) is genuine firmware, not a decompression artifact. The known-good signature is the quad at PA <text styleclass="Code Example">0xd950</text> -- a value using <text styleclass="Code Example">R2 (0xe2)</text>, never <text styleclass="Code Example">R6 (0xe6)</text>. If a future change makes the guest CPU produce <text styleclass="Code Example">R6</text> there, that is a CPU regression, not a fix.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">Deferred: a host-native boot path</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">Integrating the oracle as a runtime alternate path (<text styleclass="Code Example">--decompress=inline|host|cache</text>, default <text styleclass="Code Example">inline</text>) is deferred until the SRM console reaches the <text styleclass="Code Example">&gt;&gt;&gt;</text> prompt. The recommended design is the intercept-hybrid: let the guest huf assembly run so its CPU/PAL side-effects happen for real, intercept entry to the <text styleclass="Code Example">decompress()</text> C function, host-fill the output memory, set R0 to the decompressed base, and advance PC to the call&apos;s return site -- skipping only the multi-million-cycle inner inflate while inheriting every side-effect. A full bypass risks a subtle missing-side-effect divergence that would be painful to chase because the image bytes look perfect.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="SeeAlso">See Also.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Firmware-Decode--Decompressi">Firmware Decode &amp; Decompression</link></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Execution-_-Boot-Internals">Execution / Boot Internals</link></para>
  </body>
</topic>
