<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" status="" lasteditedby="tim" modified="2026-06-15T00:00:00.000Z" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title>Floating-Point Considerations</title>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Berkeley SoftFloat</keyword>
    <keyword>cfenv</keyword>
    <keyword>CLRFEN</keyword>
    <keyword>EMULATR_FP_SOFTFLOAT</keyword>
    <keyword>F_float</keyword>
    <keyword>fBox</keyword>
    <keyword>FEN</keyword>
    <keyword>FPCR</keyword>
    <keyword>fpBoxLib</keyword>
    <keyword>G_float</keyword>
    <keyword>HostBackend</keyword>
    <keyword>IEEE S</keyword>
    <keyword>IEEE T</keyword>
    <keyword>IFpBackend</keyword>
    <keyword>oracle</keyword>
    <keyword>rounding mode</keyword>
    <keyword>SoftFloat</keyword>
    <keyword>SoftFloatBackend</keyword>
    <keyword>trap mode</keyword>
    <keyword>VAX float</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <body>
    <header><para styleclass="Heading1">Floating-Point Considerations</para></header>
    <para styleclass="Normal">Alpha floating point is wider than a single IEEE implementation, and modeling it faithfully has several moving parts: four data formats, a separate enable gate, a control register that selects rounding and trap behavior, and a choice of compute backend. This page records the considerations a developer needs when reading or extending the fBox; it is a design overview rather than a per-opcode status table, because the instruction coverage is actively being filled in.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">Four formats</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">Alpha supports two IEEE formats -- S (single) and T (double) -- and the VAX formats F, G, and D. The distinction matters for guests: OpenVMS Alpha uses VAX G_float as its default double and F_float as its default single, while Tru64 and IEEE workloads use S and T. Data movement is format-complete: the loads and stores for all four memory formats (LDF/LDG/LDS/LDT and STF/STG/STS/STT) move values correctly, so a guest can hold VAX G_float values in registers. The work that distinguishes the formats is the arithmetic and the conversions between them, which is where build-out effort concentrates.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">The FP-enable gate</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">Floating point is gated by the FEN (FP-enable) bit. The PAL path for it is in place: MTPR_FEN and MFPR_FEN move the bit, CLRFEN clears it, and an attempt to execute FP while disabled delivers through the FEN entry vector at offset 0x200. So the enable / disabled-trap machinery works independently of how much arithmetic is implemented behind it.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">FPCR, rounding, and traps</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The floating-point control register (FPCR) selects the dynamic rounding mode and the IEEE trap-enable bits; instruction qualifiers select trap mode and rounding per-instruction. Faithful FP must honor these rather than always rounding to nearest and never signaling. The implementation approach uses the host's <text styleclass="Code Example">&lt;cfenv&gt;</text> facilities -- <text styleclass="Code Example">fesetround</text>, <text styleclass="Code Example">feclearexcept</text>, <text styleclass="Code Example">fetestexcept</text> -- around a native host operation to realize the FPCR rounding mode and to detect and deliver IEEE exceptions. Move-to / move-from FPCR provide the storage; the qualifier handling is what connects it to each operation.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">The backend abstraction</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">FP arithmetic is reached through a backend interface, <text styleclass="Code Example">IFpBackend</text> (in <text styleclass="Code Example">fpBoxLib</text>), so the grain leaves call an abstract operation set -- the IEEE S/T and VAX F/G add / subtract / multiply / divide / square-root, the compares, and the format conversions -- without binding to one implementation. Operands and results are passed as raw register images (<text styleclass="Code Example">uint64_t</text>) plus an <text styleclass="Code Example">FpExecCtx</text> that carries the rounding mode and qualifiers, and an <text styleclass="Code Example">FpResult</text> that carries the value and the exception flags. Wiring this interface into every FP grain is the in-progress integration step.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">Berkeley SoftFloat -- the deterministic oracle</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The reference implementation of <text styleclass="Code Example">IFpBackend</text> is <text styleclass="Code Example">SoftFloatBackend</text>, built on the Berkeley SoftFloat Release 3 library (vendored in the tree as <text styleclass="Code Example">berkeley-softfloat-3-master</text> and compiled into a <text styleclass="Code Example">softfloat</text> static library, 8086-SSE specialization). It is the deterministic, bit-identical-across-hosts FP truth source: the rounding mode is passed to SoftFloat as data and the exception flags are harvested as data, so no host control word (MXCSR / FPSR) is ever touched and the result is identical on every host and every build. SoftFloatBackend implements the full surface, IEEE and VAX alike, including the VAX F/G arithmetic, compares, and conversions that OpenVMS depends on.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">An optional native fast-path backend (<text styleclass="Code Example">HostBackend</text>) provides the seam for using host FP hardware where it is faster; it inherits SoftFloatBackend so any operation it has not specialized still delegates to the deterministic path, and its results are validated against SoftFloat (the <text styleclass="Code Example">fp_softfloat_vs_host_bench</text> test exists for exactly this). The build-time <text styleclass="Code Example">EMULATR_FP_SOFTFLOAT</text> option selects SoftFloat as the active backend; the longer-term aim is to expose the SoftFloat-versus-native choice as a runtime setting. Where a leaf still uses the host directly, the FPCR rounding and IEEE-trap behavior is realized with <text styleclass="Code Example">&lt;cfenv&gt;</text> as described above; the SoftFloat path needs no such host-state juggling because it carries rounding and flags as data.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="SeeAlso">See Also.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--grainFactoryLib">grainFactoryLib</link></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--CMake-Macro-Guards----------">CMake Macro Guards</link></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Attributions--Credits-------">Attributions &amp; Credits</link></para>
  </body>
</topic>
