<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" status="" lasteditedby="tim" modified="2026-06-15T00:00:00.000Z" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title>Help &amp; Manual</title>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>authoring tool</keyword>
    <keyword>documentation</keyword>
    <keyword>Help &amp; Manual</keyword>
    <keyword>help project</keyword>
    <keyword>keywords</keyword>
    <keyword>styleclass</keyword>
    <keyword>table of contents</keyword>
    <keyword>topic</keyword>
    <keyword>topiclink</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <body>
    <header><para styleclass="Heading1">Help &amp; Manual</para></header>
    <para styleclass="Normal">Help &amp; Manual (EC Software) is the documentation authoring tool that produces this help project. Every page you are reading is a Help &amp; Manual topic; the project organizes those topics into the table of contents and compiles them to the published output.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">How this documentation is structured</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">The project is one topic per subject. Each topic is an XML file with a title, a keyword index, and a body; the table of contents is a separate map that nests the topics into the eight-section structure. Pages cross-reference each other through topic links rather than copied text, so a fact lives on one page and is linked from the others.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Heading2">Authoring conventions</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal">A consistent house style keeps the project uniform: body text uses the Normal style, section headings use the Heading styles, console and code text uses the Code Example style, and a See Also block of topic links closes most pages. Two rules matter for searchability and portability -- the keyword index on each page names every noun on that page, and the text is ASCII-only (a double hyphen stands in for a dash). These are the same conventions the rest of this documentation follows.</para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="SeeAlso">See Also.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Attributions--Credits-------">Attributions &amp; Credits</link></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="--Required-Tools--Frameworks">Required Tools &amp; Frameworks</link></para>
  </body>
</topic>
